<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-03T15:56:06+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Florent Ygouf</title><subtitle>Welcome to my webpage! You can find here some information about my research and teaching activities and some other stuffs.</subtitle><author><name>Florent Ygouf</name></author><entry><title type="html">Home assignement ?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/13/home-assignement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home assignement ?" /><published>2025-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-03-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/13/home-assignement</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/03/13/home-assignement.html"><![CDATA[<p>For some time now, I have been questioning the relevance of graded homework, and this reflection has been accelerated by the democratization of generative artificial intelligence tools that can solve complex mathematical problems with just a few clicks. As an evaluator, am I assessing the work of a motivated student? Ten times the work of a motivated student copied by nine less motivated students? The work of a conversational agent? For a student, is it useful to spend hours stuck on a question that is too difficult when a little help could easily unblock the situation?</p>

<p>So, I set out to find a format for an assignment that would be interesting for students, take advantage of the diversity of tools available outside the classroom, encourage students to work in groups, and allow me to interact with them to enrich their thinking and help them in case of difficulty. I describe in this blog post the solution I found.</p>

<p>This assignment is for a class of about 90 second-year undergraduate students at the University of Rennes, the class is “Introduction to Differential Equations.” In addition to the criteria mentioned above, I designed the assignment to help students develop skills beyond those I taught them in class, which I believe are also important for understanding differential equations.</p>

<h2 id="assignment-format">Assignment Format</h2>

<p>Students will be given a text in the form of a scientific report describing the dynamics of a computer virus epidemic affecting the world’s mobile phones. They will need to model this epidemic using differential equations, the subject of the course, and then predict the evolution of the epidemic based on the parameters presented. They will need to use the tools they have learned in my course. Students will work in groups, and the work will be spread over several weeks with three key phases:</p>

<ol>
  <li>A 3-hour in-class session with two instructors. This session will focus on formulating the epidemic’s equations, and students will be encouraged to “debug” their equations by testing edge cases, the homogeneity of terms, etc. Interactions between students and instructors will be encouraged. Students will need to produce a short document explaining their approach, one per group. This document will be graded. The session will end with a summary, and the expected equations will be written on the board to ensure everyone is on solid ground for the rest of the work. Prior to this, I will send students a short video in which I will do this exercise of modeling a problem from everyday life with differential equations to familiarize them with this exercise, which is probably unusual for them at this stage.</li>
  <li>Two small-group tutorial sessions during which students can work at their own pace and ask as many questions as they wish to the instructors.</li>
  <li>A 5-minute graded oral presentation per group. Alternatively, students will be offered the option to record a 5-minute video instead. The goal of the presentation will be to synthesize their work and reflections and to highlight an aspect they consider relevant. To engage a majority of students, I have chosen to introduce an element of gamification for this step: students will have to role-play as a committee of experts addressing a report to an assembly of decision-makers seeking solutions to curb the epidemic. Beyond the fun aspect of this approach, I believe it has a pedagogical advantage: it will force students to digest and reformulate their work in concise terms.</li>
</ol>

<p>This is an intentionally open-ended assignment; there are several good ways to meet the expectations. Students will need to use their critical thinking and make choices; they will not be able to rely on a ready-made solution from a book or a web page, nor on an older sister or grandfather more advanced in mathematics, nor on a generative AI. However, they will be encouraged to use these resources! I will distribute an evaluation grid to students to guide their work and ensure the most objective grading possible. This grid will detail several directions they can take, each earning points. To encourage diverse approaches and emphasize that there are several good answers, there will be more points than the maximum grade.</p>

<h2 id="objectives-for-students">Objectives for Students</h2>

<p>I summarize in this section the objectives for students.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Learn to model everyday phenomena using differential equations.</li>
  <li>Identify the R₀ that was so widely discussed during the COVID-19 pandemic.</li>
  <li>Understand the influence of parameters on the evolution of the epidemic, and more generally, the qualitative aspects of differential equations.</li>
  <li>Gain initial experience in mathematical oral presentations.</li>
  <li>Work in groups.</li>
  <li>Learn to synthesize and reformulate.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="assignment">Assignment</h2>

<p>A computer virus is spreading globally, affecting mobile phones. A research team from the University of Rennes identified the virus and produced the following report:</p>

<p>Epidemic Dynamics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A phone is either healthy or infected.</li>
  <li>The virus is transmitted via messages: a healthy phone becomes infected when it receives a message sent from an infected phone. The</li>
  <li>reverse is not true: a healthy phone does not become infected when it sends a message to an infected phone.</li>
  <li>The virus does not destroy the phone.</li>
  <li>The virus is undetectable by users, but they can take their phone to one of the specialized centers deployed by governments worldwide. These centers can detect if the virus is present on a phone and disinfect it if necessary. However, a disinfected phone can become infected again in the future if it receives another message sent from an infected phone.</li>
</ul>

<p>Population Demographics:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The total number of phones in the population is constant.</li>
  <li>Users can discard their phone and buy a new one.</li>
  <li>The proportion of phones renewed per unit of time in the global population is constant and denoted by b.</li>
  <li>Specialized centers collectively treat a proportion γ of the world’s phone population per unit of time.</li>
  <li>Each phone sends β messages per unit of time.</li>
  <li>Healthy and infected phones are uniformly mixed in the population.</li>
  <li>Any other phenomena affecting phones must be neglected.</li>
</ul>

<p>You are a group of experts tasked with using the above report to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Model the evolution of the epidemic.</li>
  <li>Predict different scenarios based on parameter values.</li>
  <li>Present recommendations to global governments to curb the epidemic.</li>
  <li>Provide a critique of the proposed epidemiological model.</li>
</ul>

<p>You will be asked to give a 5-minute oral presentation to explain your research and findings. You will explain your approach, the tools used, and the bibliographic resources consulted. Your report should highlight the existence of a number R₀, the value of which (&lt;1 or ≥1) allows predicting the evolution of the epidemic.</p>

<h2 id="evaluation-grid">Evaluation Grid</h2>

<p>Students will have the freedom to explore several directions, each earning points. It will not be necessary to explore all directions to achieve the maximum grade. An evaluation grid will indicate which directions they can explore and the points each would earn. The possible directions are:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Visualization /4</li>
  <li>Prediction and parameter dependence (how changing parameters affects predictions, R₀) /4</li>
  <li>Clarity of presentation /5</li>
  <li>Equation formulation (produce the expected equation(s), explain each term) /5</li>
  <li>Equation resolution (existence, uniqueness, form of solutions) /8</li>
  <li>Equation debugging (homogeneity, edge cases) /2</li>
</ol>

<p>28 points, graded out of 20.</p>]]></content><author><name>Florent Ygouf</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For some time now, I have been questioning the relevance of graded homework, and this reflection has been accelerated by the democratization of generative artificial intelligence tools that can solve complex mathematical problems with just a few clicks. As an evaluator, am I assessing the work of a motivated student? Ten times the work of a motivated student copied by nine less motivated students? The work of a conversational agent? For a student, is it useful to spend hours stuck on a question that is too difficult when a little help could easily unblock the situation?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experimenting a new format in exercise session</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/02/02/experimenting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experimenting a new format in exercise session" /><published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/02/02/experimenting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/02/02/experimenting.html"><![CDATA[<p>Seeking to boost student engagement and learning outcomes, I recently implemented a new format for exercise sessions with my students at the University of Rennes. Collaborating with our university’s pedagogical support center, the <a href="https://suptice.univ-rennes.fr">suptice</a>, we collected feedback from 39 students (out of 100 surveyed) who experienced the new approach. In this post, I’ll outline the format and its advantages and limitations, as highlighted by students’ responses.</p>

<p>Quotes below come from student’s responses, the original untranslated version can be found in the appendix at the end of that post.</p>

<h2 id="traditional-exercise-class-format">Traditional exercise class format</h2>

<p>The traditional format for exercise sessions typically involves the following steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Students are given a list of exercises ahead of the session and are expected to prepare (some of) them.</li>
  <li>During the session, a solution for each exercise is provided on the board to all students at once, either by the instructor or by the students themselves, under the supervision of the tutor. Sometimes, students are given some times in between two corrections to have time to think about the next exercice.</li>
  <li>After the session, if needed, students go through their notes taken in class to make sure they have assimilated the solutions.</li>
</ol>

<p>This format works well for students who prepare carefully before class, solve exercises or clearly identify sticking points, and can follow corrections in real-time. However:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Many students come in class unprepared.</li>
  <li>Following complex proofs or arguments in real-time can be tough and students might opt out and passively copy solutions instead, needing to revisit the material later.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Students have different paces and may feel sessions dwell too long on certain topics and not enough on others.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Some exercises require more time, while others are simpler. This can be due to the intrinsic difficulty of the exercise, but also to personal preferences. Having a set pace for corrections can sometimes be extremely frustrating when the exercise is corrected too slowly, or conversely, when there hasn’t been enough time to work on it sufficiently.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Suppose each one-hour session requires 1 hour of preparation and 1 hour for processing. With 7 hours of tutoring per week, this totals 21 hours of work weekly, just for exercises.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Advanced students who can solve exercises independently may not gain much from this system and might skip class.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="new-experimental-format">New experimental format</h2>

<p>To address the challenges mentionned above, I am trying the following format:</p>

<ol>
  <li>At the start of the semester, students receive a pre-prepared exercise booklet with around 30 exercises and detailed solutions.</li>
  <li>Students are asked to review their lessons at home before the exercise session but are not expected to work on the exercises.</li>
  <li>During the session, students work independently on exercises while the instructor circulates to answer questions and assess progress.</li>
</ol>

<p>Among the 39 repondants, 69% found the new format was an improvement compared to the usual format.</p>

<h3 id="benefits-for-students">Benefits for students</h3>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Students can now work at their own pace.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>It is enjoyable to be able to work at one’s own pace, to move directly to the solution if one feels stuck and cannot overcome the obstacle, and to spend more time on a specific exercise where one is struggling or to move faster when one has understood the concept.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Everyone works at their own pace, which fosters a stronger desire to engage in their tasks. On a personal note, I haven’t experienced the feeling of not performing well after any tutorial sessions for this course.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Students can ask individualized questions without having to speak out in front of the whole class, which seems to be a strong inhibitor.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Instead of spending tutorial sessions copying exercise solutions, we can spend time understanding the exercises and asking the professor questions.</p>
    </blockquote>

    <blockquote>
      <p>Advantages of the format included: Feedback, listening, regular individual interaction with the teacher, the choice to present certain results with a reflection on their usefulness, emphasizing the intuition that leads to their discovery.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>This creates a space in students’ schedule clearly identified to productive working.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>The sessions were far more effective as I actively engaged with the exercises, leading to a deeper understanding and better retention of the methods compared to traditional tutorials.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Student can help each other, which I believe should be encouraged.</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>I enjoyed the possiblity of sharing ideas with other students while doing the exercises.</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Advanced students can be given additional marterial as needed.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="benefits-for-instructors">Benefits for instructors</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Everything is prepared in advance, runs smoothly and is recyclable.</li>
  <li>Instructors can better assess the sticking points and the progression of each individual.</li>
  <li>The experience is more enjoyable as students engage more, and face-to-face conversations are more stimulating than a class of potentially passive students.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="potential-risks-and-fixes">Potential risks and fixes:</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Students, having all the material at hand, might be tempted to skip class if they don’t see the value of attending the session. To encourage students to complete the exercises diligently, they are informed that half of the points they can score during exams are based on exercises covered in the exercise booklet. This approach not only motivates students but also makes pedagogical sense, as understanding and reproducing familiar reasoning is core to mathematical practice.</li>
  <li>Students may remain too shy to ask for help when needed. Every one once in a while, I ask them to explain to me what they are doing to engage with them.</li>
  <li>Students may adopt a “linear reading” or not spend enough time on a solution and miss key points. I usually pick an exercise representative of the session and explain the main steps of the solution on the board at the end of each session.</li>
  <li>Noisy sessions can undermine the effort to create a productive and focused atmosphere.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Not explaining the format well enough to other instructors and/or ensuring it is carefully followed can induce frustration in students</p>

    <blockquote>
      <p>The noise level was quite high, and there wasn’t much support from the tutor, aside from occasionally answering questions (when they actually addressed the questions…).</p>
    </blockquote>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>

<p>Preparing such a format of class is demanding the first time it is given, but it is rewarding to see students engage more and witness their ‘ah-ah’ moments in real-time. At my university, we have the option to give the same class several years in a row, and I believe this approach eventually saves time, especially if adopted by other colleagues as it requires very little preparation from tutors. It is important, however, that everyone involved be aware of the limitations explained above to ensure its success. I am trying this format again this semester after making a few tweaks based on the feedback we collected. Overall, I really enjoy this approach, and it seems to be, for the most part, praised by students!</p>

<h2 id="appendices">Appendices</h2>

<ol>
  <li>The raw <a href="/assets/pdf/eval_suptice.pdf">file</a> (in French) with student responses to the questionnaire. I am flagging that a tutor in one of the 3 groups did not follow the format, which explains some of the answers.</li>
  <li>The <a href="/assets/pdf/ED1_fascicule_exercices.pdf">booklet</a> distributed to students.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Florent Ygouf</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Seeking to boost student engagement and learning outcomes, I recently implemented a new format for exercise sessions with my students at the University of Rennes. Collaborating with our university’s pedagogical support center, the suptice, we collected feedback from 39 students (out of 100 surveyed) who experienced the new approach. In this post, I’ll outline the format and its advantages and limitations, as highlighted by students’ responses.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A new webpage!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/19/new-webpage.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new webpage!" /><published>2025-01-19T23:10:54+01:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T23:10:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/19/new-webpage</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2025/01/19/new-webpage.html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new website! I built it using Jekyll with the Minima theme. It took some time to get the hang of it, but now updating and managing the site will be much more enjoyable. If you’d like to learn more about Jekyll, check out this <a href="https://jekyllrb.com">link</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Florent Ygouf</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new website! I built it using Jekyll with the Minima theme. It took some time to get the hang of it, but now updating and managing the site will be much more enjoyable. If you’d like to learn more about Jekyll, check out this link.]]></summary></entry></feed>